<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://mongoliandatastories.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://mongoliandatastories.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-05-10T13:16:19+08:00</updated><id>https://mongoliandatastories.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Mongolian Data Stories</title><subtitle>Telling Mongolia's story through data.</subtitle><author><name>Robert Ritz</name></author><entry><title type="html">Mongolia’s $150,000 license plate</title><link href="https://mongoliandatastories.com/Mongolias-150-000-License-Plate" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Mongolia’s $150,000 license plate" /><published>2021-02-15T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2021-02-15T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>https://mongoliandatastories.com/Mongolias-150-000-License-Plate</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mongoliandatastories.com/Mongolias-150-000-License-Plate">&lt;h4 id=&quot;would-you-pay-this-much-for-the-countrys-best-licenseplate&quot;&gt;Would you pay this much for the country’s “best” license plate?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TL:DR&lt;/strong&gt; Mongolia auctions off a “lucky number” license plate and the bids reach 427.45 million MNT (Mongolian Tugriks) in &lt;strong&gt;less than three hours&lt;/strong&gt;. That’s $150,035.10 USD at current exchange rates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Numbers mean a lot to most Mongolians. Generally, 1, 3, 8, and 9 are considered “lucky” numbers. Mongolian phone numbers have 8 digits, and the first 4 of these numbers can tell you a lot about who is calling you. So-called “lucky” phone numbers beginning with 99 or 88 regularly sell for anywhere from $1,000 (9999-XXXX) up to $20,000 or more for the most elite (9911-XXXX). These phone numbers are sold on the “secondary market” from person to person. If a 9911-XXXX number calls you and you don’t answer, expect them to be upset…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, license plate numbers are assigned to a vehicle and can’t be transferred between individuals. In addition, up until recently, you couldn’t pay for a better license plate number. This caused a situation where the “best” license plates (think 0001-УБА) &lt;em&gt;somehow&lt;/em&gt; ended up on Mercedes G-Wagon’s and Land Cruisers. I wonder how that happened?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/mongolias-150000-license-plate/g-wagon.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;The G-Wagon. &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Mercedes-Benz_G_63_AMG_2012.JPG&quot;&gt;Source: Wikimedia Commons&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The general public always knew what was really happening. At one point frustration was so high that there was discussion of giving these lucky numbers to garbage trucks or other city vehicles. It seems their voice was heard when the new &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.legalinfo.mn/annex/details/11395?lawid=15748&quot;&gt;Motor Vehicle Registration Country Number Procedure&lt;/a&gt; was approved in late 2020. This procedure set up a system to allow “lucky” numbers to be auctioned on the &lt;a href=&quot;http://Vehicle%20registration%20department&quot;&gt;Vehicle Registration Department’s website&lt;/a&gt;. This has been generally viewed as a positive development, as those willing to pay for this special license plate could pay legally for the privilege and contribute to government revenue and social programs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not sure anyone expected what happened next. On February 15, 2021, the number 0001-УАР had its day to be auctioned. The first bid was 1,000,000 MNT (approximately $350 USD). Let’s see what happened…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/mongolias-150000-license-plate/chart.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cumulative bids for various license plates on February 15, 2021. Source: Author&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The auction opened at 9:00AM. In less than 30 minutes bids for 0001-УАР reached the equivalent of $100,000. By 11:30AM the auction total reached 427.45 million MNT (Mongolian Tugriks). &lt;strong&gt;That’s $150,035.10 USD at current exchange rates.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;width:100%;height:0;padding-bottom:56%;position:relative;&quot;&gt;&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://giphy.com/embed/ToMjGpjpXMFPshSYGLm&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;100%&quot; style=&quot;position:absolute&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; class=&quot;giphy-embed&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://giphy.com/gifs/editingandlayout-anchorman-that-escalated-quickly-ToMjGpjpXMFPshSYGLm&quot;&gt;via GIPHY&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyone bidding on a license plate number is required to put in a deposit for their bid of 50,000 MNT (about $17 USD). There were 957 bids for 0001-УАР. Those who didn’t win the auction will have their deposits returned. The winning bid is now expected to pay the total amount. If they don’t pay or are unable to, this number will go up for auction again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s unclear how much of this auction was real interest or social media hype, as this particular license plate went somewhat viral on various Mongolian language Facebook groups. To put things in perspective, the average yearly salary in Ulaanbaatar, the capital, is about $5,300 USD.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What do you think? Is a $150,000 license plate worth it?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Robert Ritz</name></author><category term="auction" /><category term="lucky numbers" /><summary type="html">Would you pay this much for the country’s “best” license plate?</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://mongoliandatastories.com/images/mongolias-150000-license-plate/cover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://mongoliandatastories.com/images/mongolias-150000-license-plate/cover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Sqair Air Purifier Real World Test</title><link href="https://mongoliandatastories.com/Sqair-real-world-test" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sqair Air Purifier Real World Test" /><published>2019-09-18T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2019-09-18T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>https://mongoliandatastories.com/Sqair-real-world-test</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mongoliandatastories.com/Sqair-real-world-test">&lt;h4 id=&quot;i-put-the-new-sqair-air-purifier-from-smart-air-to-the-test-in-a-controlled-experiment&quot;&gt;I put the new Sqair air purifier from Smart Air to the test in a controlled experiment&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;note-i-was-loaned-a-test-unit-and-i-did-not-receive-any-payment-or-renumeration-from-smart-air-for-this-article&quot;&gt;Note: I was loaned a test unit, and I did not receive any payment or renumeration from Smart Air for this article.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Winter is coming, and we know what that means in Ulaanbaatar. Extremely high levels of air pollution. Even with the recent &lt;a href=&quot;https://montsame.mn/en/read/189503&quot;&gt;ban on the burning of raw coal&lt;/a&gt; it is possible (even likely) that levels of the particularly dangerous pollutant PM2.5 will remain high during the winter months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During these months a pollution mask and air purifier are essential equipment to protect yourself and your family. Air purifiers can cost anywhere from $150-$500 or more. This means many families choose to forgo air purifiers completely, at the cost of their entire families health. Smart Air, a social enterprise founded in 2013, wants to change this situation with the launch of their new no-nonsense air purifier, the Sqair. Funded through a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kickstarter.com/projects/smartair/the-sqair-the-worlds-most-cost-effective-air-purifier/description&quot;&gt;Kickstarter campaign&lt;/a&gt; in June, the Sqair purports to be the world’s most cost effective air purifier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/sqair-real-world-test/top.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
*Top view of the Sqair. Simple rotating controls.**&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/sqair-real-world-test/left.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;The Sqair in our small 10m² test room.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sqair was kind enough to lend me a unit for a few days to test it out. I’ll first give my general thoughts on the device and then present my experiment to show how effective the Sqair is at removing PM2.5 from a room.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was very pleased with the look of the device as it didn’t stick out as much as other air purifiers (the IQ Air purifier looks like an industrial battery). The controls are dead simple with three options: off, 1, 2, and 3. &lt;em&gt;Fan speed 1&lt;/em&gt; is very quiet (like very quiet). &lt;em&gt;Fan speed 2&lt;/em&gt; is certainly audible even in a room with a little background noise, but it easily blends in. &lt;em&gt;Fan speed 3&lt;/em&gt; is downright noisy, but as you will see below there isn’t much need to use this speed unless you are looking to really move some air through the machine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-experiment&quot;&gt;The Experiment&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing I really wanted to test was how effective the Sqair is at clearing pollution from a room. I’ve heard criticism about air purifiers from several people who are skeptical of how well they circulate air. The common question is, “How do I know it isn’t just cleaning the air in one corner of the room?”. So I set up an experiment to see how well the Sqair works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At my school we have a quiet study room that is 10m² and has ceilings of 3 meters. That makes 30 cubic meters of air in the room. The room has a door that seals completely and has no air vents. This made the perfect room to conduct an experiment with an air purifier. The only problem is that in early September there is essentially no air pollution outside, and inside PM2.5 levels hover around 5 µg/m³. So I had to get creative and make some air pollution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/sqair-real-world-test/camera-sensor.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Timelapse camera pointing at a laser PM2.5 sensor.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/sqair-real-world-test/pollution-source.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Artificial pollution source (арц).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Mongolia арц (ground Juniper leaf) is commonly burned for religious purposes. It turns out it also is a great source of PM2.5! I poured a few grams of the green powder in a cup and lit it up. The sensor I was using maxes out around 1,500 µg/m³, and after only a few minutes of burning it reached the max! Keep in mind that air is considered “good” by the US EPA if the PM2.5 level is below an average of 12 µg/m³ over 24 hours (the Mongolian standard states that the air is clean below an average of 50 µg/m³ over 24 hours)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used the following process to run the experiment:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The air purifier and air quality sensor were placed on opposite sides of the room.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Burn the арц for a few minutes until the PM2.5 level spikes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Set the air purifier to a speed.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wait for 90 minutes while the camera records a timelapse of the air quality sensor.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I also ran a separate test with the air purifier off for 90 minutes to set a baseline.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The results were quite amazing! It’s one thing to know that your air purifier is keeping your air clean, it’s another to see it working in real-time. Let’s take a look at the results:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;h/images/sqair-real-world-test/chart.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before running the test I was quite concerned that the very very quite speed 1 wouldn’t circulate the air enough to clean the room’s air. It turns out that even on fan speed 1 the air was being cleaned at a very steady rate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the fan speed 2 test, it seemed the air was moving around quite a bit more, and for a brief time, the PM2.5 levels went down and then up again. The fan speed 3 test was almost comical in how quickly the air was cleaned. I actually ended it early because I saw no use in continuing it after 60 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall the results were what I expected for speeds 2, and 3, but better than expected for speed 1. In a larger room, fan speed 1 &lt;em&gt;may&lt;/em&gt; not circulate air enough to clean it well. However, this will depend greatly on the room and I couldn’t give a definitive answer based on my test.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was quite impressed with the simplicity, effectiveness, and cost of the Sqair. It just works and it does so while looking good and not breaking the bank. I can easily recommend these air purifiers to anyone looking for a simple and cost-effective solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are interested in buying a Sqair or learning more about Smart Air check out their website &lt;a href=&quot;https://smartairfilters.com/mn/en/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Robert Ritz</name></author><category term="pollution" /><summary type="html">I put the new Sqair air purifier from Smart Air to the test in a controlled experiment</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://mongoliandatastories.com/images/sqair-real-world-test/cover.jpeg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://mongoliandatastories.com/images/sqair-real-world-test/cover.jpeg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Mongolian Electoral District Analysis 2020</title><link href="https://mongoliandatastories.com/Mongolian-Electoral-District-Demographic-Analysis" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Mongolian Electoral District Analysis 2020" /><published>2019-06-17T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2019-06-17T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>https://mongoliandatastories.com/Mongolian-Electoral-District-Demographic-Analysis</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mongoliandatastories.com/Mongolian-Electoral-District-Demographic-Analysis">&lt;h4 id=&quot;2020-parliamentary-election&quot;&gt;2020 Parliamentary Election&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The current election saw a switch back to the block voting system used in 1992 and 2008. This system has both &lt;a href=&quot;http://blogs.ubc.ca/mongolia/2019/plurality-at-large-voting-revisited-for-2020/&quot;&gt;positives and negatives&lt;/a&gt;, and this system has much larger election districts than the previous single-member districts of the 2016 election. This allows us to more easily analyze the districts with the available data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To put all of the data together and make it user friendly, I built &lt;a href=&quot;https://songolt.org&quot;&gt;Songolt&lt;/a&gt;, an interactive data explorer that allows the reader to see key indicators of election districts. The indicators covered in the app include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Population indicators&lt;/strong&gt;: population, household size, herder percent, age group breakdown&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Economic indicators (self-reported)&lt;/strong&gt;: salary, household loans, employment, education levels&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Quality of life indicators&lt;/strong&gt;: crime, house type, toilet &amp;amp; water type, heating type&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The data was collected from &lt;a href=&quot;http://1212.mn&quot;&gt;1212.mn&lt;/a&gt; and also the &lt;a href=&quot;http://web.nso.mn/nada/index.php/catalog/115&quot;&gt;Household Socioeconomic Survey of 2016&lt;/a&gt;, which is the latest survey that contains precise geographic labeling. Both data sources are maintained by the National Statistics Office of Mongolia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Several themes developed through my research into this data. These themes are perhaps not surprising for many readers familiar with Mongolia, but it is never a bad thing to back up observations with data. I encourage you, the reader, to explore the app yourself (&lt;a href=&quot;https://songolt.org&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;), but below I give an overview of the themes for your convenience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;ulaanbaatar-vs-countryside&quot;&gt;Ulaanbaatar vs Countryside&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the best-known difference in Mongolia is that of Ulaanbaatar and the countryside. The image of busy urban Ulaanbaatar juxtaposed with the bucolic countryside could hardly be more different. Indeed the data shows significant differences in many areas. Let’s compare the population pyramid for the election district with the highest population, Songinokhairkhan District in Ulaanbaatar, with the least populace, Bulgan Aimag.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/mongolian-electoral-analysis-2020/population-pyramid.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is an obvious population difference, but the size of the age groups also shows a marked difference between the two. Where you have a large spike in the 20–40 age group in Songinokhairkhan, Bulgans’ age groups have much less variability and are quite flat from 15–50. You will see a similar trend in the highest population election districts compared with the least populated ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means the voting demographics in rural areas are more widely distributed than in urban areas. D.Byambjav and E.Gerelt-Od &lt;a href=&quot;http://blogs.ubc.ca/mongolia/2020/voter-demography/&quot;&gt;previously discussed&lt;/a&gt; the large and less engaged block of voters under 35. If youth engagement initiatives are successful, this block of voters will be less powerful in rural districts that have a similar age distribution to Bulgan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/mongolian-electoral-analysis-2020/percentage-employed.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Employment differs significantly as well between Ulaanbaatar and most rural districts. Rural election districts tend to show significantly higher rates of overall employment than the urban ones. In the chart above, the “employed percentage” refers to the proportion of the working-age population that is employed. Urban districts tend to have between 45–55% employment, with rural districts between 65–75%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/mongolian-electoral-analysis-2020/average-salary.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Salaries are also significantly higher in Ulaanbaatar. The salaries shown above are self-reported from 2016, but they show a very clear picture. Employment levels may be higher in rural areas, but salary levels are conversely lower. This is an obvious area where the &lt;a href=&quot;http://blogs.ubc.ca/mongolia/2020/guest-post-economic-policy-party-platforms/&quot;&gt;economic policy of the party platforms&lt;/a&gt; could address these inequalities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;outliers-mining-areas-and-bayan-ulgii&quot;&gt;Outliers: Mining Areas and Bayan-Ulgii&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Ulaanbaatar vs countryside theme may be the biggest theme in the data, it doesn’t give the full picture. There are two sets of outliers that “buck the trend”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first is that the two primary mining areas of Mongolia, Erdenet (in Orkhon) and Oyu Toloig (in Umnugovi), show significantly higher salaries, lower loan rates, and higher educations than other rural election districts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/mongolian-electoral-analysis-2020/loans-vs-salary.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This bubble plot shows the percent of households with loans vs monthly average salaries in each election district. The two highlighted in red are Orkhon (lower right) and Umnugovi (upper left). All of the bubbles above 550k average monthly salary except for the two in red are located in Ulaanbaatar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These two election districts (and the urban workforce where the company offices are) have benefited heavily from the mining industry of Mongolia. Industrialization as proposed in the party platforms would most likely further benefit these areas, as this is where the raw materials would come from.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/mongolian-electoral-analysis-2020/loans-vs-salary2.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second outlier is Bayan-Ulgii. In the chart above, the red bubble to the farthest left is Bayan-Ulgii, and the red bubble on the far right is Khan-Uul District. The average household size is 5.2, significantly larger than the most populace district Songinokhairkhan of 3.8. Besides larger family sizes, Bayan-Ulgii has the lowest average monthly salary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;ulaanbaatar-districts-have-diverseneeds&quot;&gt;Ulaanbaatar Districts Have Diverse Needs&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The districts of Ulaanbaatar also show diverse needs. Every district also contains part of the ger district. This means that there is a mix of urban and peri-urban in every election district of Ulaanbaatar. In the center of the city, households are connected to the central water, heating, and sewage systems. In the ger district, living standards become sharply different, with no central heat or water connections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/mongolian-electoral-analysis-2020/heating-type.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The unique layout of the city districts ensures that at least 20% of the population of each district uses pit toilets and wood or coal for heat. More than 40% of Khan-Uul district households, the most affluent election district in Mongolia, use ordinary wood and coal stoves for heat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;mps-will-represent-very-diversegroups&quot;&gt;MPs Will Represent Very Diverse Groups&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regardless of the outcome of the election, it is clear that the needs of citizens in election districts are not uniform, and even the common trope of UB vs the rest doesn’t hold up completely. Even though Mongolia a small country with a heavy focus on mining, it isn’t clear that the party platforms address the inequalities mentioned above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the economics platforms of the DP, MPP, and Right Person Electorate all &lt;a href=&quot;http://blogs.ubc.ca/mongolia/2020/guest-post-economic-policy-party-platforms/&quot;&gt;focus on heavy industry&lt;/a&gt;, it isn’t clear how heavy industry would help rural areas outside of the main mining areas lacking in high paying jobs, or whether it would increase employment levels in Ulaanbaatar.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Robert Ritz</name></author><category term="election" /><category term="parliament" /><summary type="html">2020 Parliamentary Election</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://mongoliandatastories.com/images/mongolian-electoral-analysis-2020/cover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://mongoliandatastories.com/images/mongolian-electoral-analysis-2020/cover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The Ethical Matrix of Dzud Forecasting</title><link href="https://mongoliandatastories.com/Ethical-matrix-dzud-forecasting" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Ethical Matrix of Dzud Forecasting" /><published>2019-02-13T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2019-02-13T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>https://mongoliandatastories.com/Ethical-matrix-dzud-forecasting</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mongoliandatastories.com/Ethical-matrix-dzud-forecasting">&lt;p&gt;In 2016 a pivotal book in the field of data science was released. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Weapons-Math-Destruction-Increases-Inequality-ebook/dp/B01LDFCP0S/ref=sr_1_1?keywords=weapons+of+math+destruction&amp;amp;qid=1549790280&amp;amp;s=gateway&amp;amp;sr=8-1&quot;&gt;Weapons of Math Destruction&lt;/a&gt;, by Cathy O’Neil, makes the claim that the algorithms which promise to change our world for the better can also reinforce discrimination, unfair bias, and cause damage on a massive scale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this book and in a forthcoming research paper, O’Neil proposes that algorithms don’t just predict the future, they can also &lt;em&gt;create it.&lt;/em&gt; As such she proposes the use of an “Ethical Matrix” be completed before such an algorithm is implemented. This matrix is designed to understand the real impact of an algorithm. It aims to explicitly answer &lt;em&gt;who the algorithm is impacting and how&lt;/em&gt; in the following ways:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fairness: is the algorithm truly fair to all those impacted?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Transparency: do we have visibility as to how the algorithm is making its decisions?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;False Negatives: how are stakeholders impacted by false negatives?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;False Positives: how are stakeholders impacted by false positives?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why is this matrix important? As algorithms are being applied in more areas of our lives, there is often little regard to their full impact. Here are just a few examples of algorithms and their unintended consequences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In 2015 Google’s auto-tagging photo feature embarrassed the company by labeling a black person a gorilla. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wired.com/story/when-it-comes-to-gorillas-google-photos-remains-blind/&quot;&gt;Google still has this problem.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Recently a significant amount of scrutiny was placed on &lt;a href=&quot;https://qz.com/1276781/algorithms-are-making-the-same-mistakes-assessing-credit-scores-that-humans-did-a-century-ago/&quot;&gt;algorithmic credit scoring&lt;/a&gt;. These supposedly fair algorithms show a surprising bias in areas such as race. In one example an algorithm reduced credit scores for customers that had a bank charge for “counseling”.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Amazon has used an algorithm to assess recruits applying for jobs at the company. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reuters.com/article/us-amazon-com-jobs-automation-insight/amazon-scraps-secret-ai-recruiting-tool-that-showed-bias-against-women-idUSKCN1MK08G&quot;&gt;This algorithm&lt;/a&gt; appeared to have a strong gender bias against women. Amazon says they never put it in production.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/syncedreview/2018-in-review-10-ai-failures-c18faadf5983&quot; title=&quot;https://medium.com/syncedreview/2018-in-review-10-ai-failures-c18faadf5983&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2018 in Review: 10 AI Failures&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
_Last December Synced compiled its first “Artificial Intelligence Failures” recap of AI gaffes from the previous year…_medium.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/syncedreview/2018-in-review-10-ai-failures-c18faadf5983&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given these potential consequences, it’s a good idea to evaluate any potential new algorithm to better understand how it could hurt those it impacts. A recently released algorithm in Mongolia inspired me to do just this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;livestock-mortality-index&quot;&gt;Livestock Mortality Index&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In November 2018 a &lt;a href=&quot;https://reliefweb.int/report/mongolia/advancing-understanding-dzud-risk-livestock-mortality-model-and-multi-indicator-dzud&quot;&gt;research paper&lt;/a&gt; was released by People in Need, an international NGO, that proposes a livestock mortality index to perhaps provide an early warning for &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zud&quot;&gt;dzud&lt;/a&gt; in Mongolia. This index would assign a value from 0–5 for each aimag (province) that would describe the risk of dzud in that aimag for the next winter. As dzud is perhaps the largest natural disaster Mongolia faces, being able to accurately assess the risk of dzud is a very important step in making herding a sustainable livelihood long term.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently, the Government of Mongolia has a &lt;a href=&quot;http://eic.mn/dzud/index.php&quot;&gt;risk map model&lt;/a&gt; (at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sum_%28country_subdivision%29&quot;&gt;soum&lt;/a&gt; level) in place that was implemented in 2015/2016 and is updated every 10 days. The way in which the proposed index is different is the lead time it would provide to prepare areas that are at the highest risk. Instead of identifying a sudden issue up to 10 days in advance, there would be an indicator of risk months ahead of time. This would give the government and non-governmental actors time to preposition fodder or other materials long before a dzud occurred.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the paper, the authors make clear that this index is not intended to be a forecast, but rather an indicator of risk. However, as this is essentially an algorithm that is attempting to predict the future, I thought this was the perfect time to apply the Ethical Matrix to a Mongolian case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ethical-matrix&quot;&gt;Ethical Matrix&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To assess the algorithm we will look at four areas: &lt;strong&gt;fairness, transparency, false negatives,&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;false positives&lt;/strong&gt;. To quickly summarize the algorithm, it uses 7 indicators to create a score from 0–5 (ex. 0.1, 1.4, 2.3, 4, 4.4) for each aimag. The higher the number the higher the risk. The indicators are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Winter temperature anomaly&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Snowfall anomaly&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Biomass anomaly&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pasture use anomaly&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Zootechnical scores (a combination of past mortality and female reproductivity)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;fairness&quot;&gt;Fairness&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea of fairness is the general question of whether the algorithm treats those impacted by it equally. In this, the algorithm does quite well. One area of concern is the metric of forage biomass (the amount of forage available). Given the disparity between the south of Mongolia and the north, this is an area where an imbalance could occur. The authors handle this by looking at the anomaly (or change in) biomass to ensure areas with disparate biomass are not treated differently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/ethical-matrix-dzud-forecasting/biomass.gif&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;transparency&quot;&gt;Transparency&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transparency in an algorithm is a difficult thing to accomplish. As these are computer models, it isn’t as simple as asking the computer ‘&lt;em&gt;Why did you do that?’&lt;/em&gt;. However, what we can do is understand how the inputs are related to the outputs. For example, if I change one thing how does this change the score (higher/lower). In this way, we can understand “how” the algorithm is coming to its conclusions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The algorithm here again does this quite well. As it is a linear model, we have coefficients for each variable. These coefficients are basically weights on the variables that are combined with the variables themselves to generate a score. The model equation is given and as such we can determine how each variable impacts the final risk score.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/ethical-matrix-dzud-forecasting/page16.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Page 16 of the MDVI report&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;false-positives-and-negatives&quot;&gt;False Positives and Negatives&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s great to have a fair and transparent algorithm, but what if it fails in certain ways that can cause harm? This is what we try to assess when looking at false positives and false negatives. A false positive in this case is a high-risk score (a “positive” result for high dzud risk) when little to no mortality occurred. The opposite situation is a false negative, where the risk score is low but high mortality results. Both are undesirable but for different reasons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;False Positives&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A false positive is also known as “crying wolf”. The result can be similar to the fable, with an erosion of trust in the model after several attempts to prevent disaster over the long term. In the short term, a false positive can waste resources that could otherwise be used in areas that need them more. Over the long term, the larger movement to stop a dzud from happening could be undermined with herders, governments, and NGO’s withdrawing from the program.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea of &lt;a href=&quot;http://blogs.ubc.ca/mongolia/2017/crying-wolf-dzud/&quot;&gt;false dzud alarms&lt;/a&gt; was discussed in 2017 by Julian Dierkes, a professor at the University of British Columbia and a well-known observer of Mongolia. This critical look at false positives shows how not only data can undermine the system, but the perception of the situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;False Negative&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A false negative can have dire consequences. In this situation, high mortality would occur with the model indicating a low risk. This would mean that enough fodder or other materials may not be readily available on short notice to help in aimags falsely designated as low risk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This would have more extreme short term consequences not only for livestock but also for trust in the model. If a model has even a few false negatives it very likely could be thrown out and labeled untrustworthy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;confusion-matrix&quot;&gt;Confusion Matrix&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In general, when optimizing a machine learning model it is good to ask whether false positives or false negatives are worse. For this model, it is conceivable that several false positives could be tolerated, although with an erosion of trust and possibly less mobilization for each subsequent false positive. However, it would be disastrous to have even a few false negatives in the real world. Livestock could die by the hundreds of thousands and the area could be devastated economically. For this reason, I believe that false negatives for this are much less desirable and should be minimized as much as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The authors of the study made available the predicted risk scores and the livestock mortality numbers for the years in question. With this data, we can create a confusion matrix that will allow us to visualize our false positives and negatives. As the authors did not give bins for the index values, we will simplify things a bit and bin them ourselves. The bins are as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Index, Mortality %&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;0–1, [0%-3%]&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1–2, (3%-6%]&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2–3, (6%-17%]&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;3+, (17%+)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is the corresponding confusion matrix. TP = True Positive, TN = True Negative, FP = False Positive, FN = False Negative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/ethical-matrix-dzud-forecasting/confusion-matrix.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Confusion matrix derived from MVDI risk scores&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Viewing this confusion matrix we see a relatively small number of true positives or negatives (about 15% of the total). If this were a classification task this would be quite undesirable. However, the model is set up as a regression task, so this isn’t necessarily bad. Of more interest are the FP’s and FN’s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The false positives are the large majority here. As we established that we want to minimize FN’s due to their destructive potential, this is a positive sign. However, FP’s are nearly 74% of the values. Given this, it should be known that this model will consistently overstate the risk values.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One way to solve the issue with FP’s and FN’s is to restate the task as a classification one. Currently, as regression, the output plotted against real values is shown in figure 5. While it’s simple to say that higher values mean higher risk, what is one aimag has “1.5” and the other has “2.2”. Should more resources be provided to the higher risk even though we know this model has a high false positive ratio?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/ethical-matrix-dzud-forecasting/mdvi-index-chart.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Resulting index values from MDVI model&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By changing the problem to a classification one we can allow the user of the model to make more intuitive decisions from the output of the model. Instead of numeric values, the output of the model could be “low”, “medium”, and “high”. This may in itself be too simple, but if the classes are based on actual results from real data, then they will have a higher interpretive ability in the real world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is an important step for any machine learning or algorithmic project to take time to understand how it’s results can impact stakeholders and the system as a whole. The authors state that this model was not designed as a dzud forecast. However, once they release it in the real world NGO’s and governments can interpret the results how they wish. As such, there is a very real responsibility to understand how these values can be interpreted.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Robert Ritz</name></author><category term="dzud" /><category term="forecasting" /><summary type="html">In 2016 a pivotal book in the field of data science was released. Weapons of Math Destruction, by Cathy O’Neil, makes the claim that the algorithms which promise to change our world for the better can also reinforce discrimination, unfair bias, and cause damage on a massive scale.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://mongoliandatastories.com/images/ethical-matrix-dzud-forecasting/cover.jpeg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://mongoliandatastories.com/images/ethical-matrix-dzud-forecasting/cover.jpeg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The Tsagaan Sar Debt Cycle</title><link href="https://mongoliandatastories.com/Tsagaan-Sar-debt-cycle" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Tsagaan Sar Debt Cycle" /><published>2019-02-08T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2019-02-08T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>https://mongoliandatastories.com/Tsagaan-Sar-debt-cycle</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mongoliandatastories.com/Tsagaan-Sar-debt-cycle">&lt;p&gt;The entire country mobilizes weeks ahead of time to prepare. The city government, worried about traffic, only allows cars to drive during alternate days on the weekend. The bakeries are so consumed with making &lt;em&gt;ul boov&lt;/em&gt;, a traditional pastry, that bread starts to disappear from store shelves the week before the holiday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This sounds like quite a lot, but it is just the run-up to the actual event, Tsagaan Sar, Mongolia’s lunar new year celebration. The main activity of the holiday (which goes on for three days) is where family (and extended family) visit their elders in their home. The guests traditionally bring money as a gift for their elders, and the guests are given gifts (sometimes small, sometimes large) in addition to a truly magnificent feast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The video below shows the preparation of one of the signature dishes of Tsagaan Sar, &lt;em&gt;buuz&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tsagaan Sar Preparation&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/BymB9IYd2xE&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-cost&quot;&gt;The Cost&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each year new outlets write many articles sharing the costs of Tsagaan Sar. &lt;a href=&quot;https://news.mn/r/770526/&quot;&gt;News.mn estimated&lt;/a&gt; this year that cost for one family is about 1.32 million MNT (about $500 USD). To put his in perspective, more than half of those employed make less than &lt;a href=&quot;http://dnn.mn/%D1%86%D0%B0%D0%B3%D0%B0%D0%B0%D0%BD-%D1%81%D0%B0%D1%80-%D0%B1%D0%B0-%D1%86%D0%B0%D0%BB%D0%B8%D0%BD-%D1%82%D1%8D%D1%82%D0%B3%D1%8D%D0%B2%D1%8D%D1%80%D0%B8%D0%B9%D0%BD-%D0%B7%D1%8D%D1%8D%D0%BB/&quot;&gt;$200 per month&lt;/a&gt;. A survey completed by a market research firm and reported by &lt;a href=&quot;http://bloombergtv.mn/%D0%B8%D1%80%D0%B3%D1%8D%D0%B4%D0%B8%D0%B9%D0%BD-62-%D1%85%D1%83%D0%B2%D1%8C-%D0%BD%D1%8C-%D0%B7%D1%8D%D1%8D%D0%BB%D1%8D%D1%8D%D1%80-%D1%86%D0%B0%D0%B3%D0%B0%D0%B0%D0%BD-%D1%81%D0%B0%D1%80-%D1%82%D1%8D%D0%BC%D0%B4%D1%8D%D0%B3%D0%BB%D1%8D%D0%B6-357-%D1%82%D1%8D%D1%80%D0%B1%D1%83%D0%BC-%D1%82%D3%A9%D0%B3%D1%80%D3%A9%D0%B3%D0%B8%D0%B9%D0%B3-%D0%B8%D0%BC%D0%BF%D0%BE%D1%80%D1%82%D1%8B%D0%BD-%D0%B1%D1%8D%D0%BB%D1%8D%D0%B3%D1%82-%D0%B7%D0%B0%D1%80%D1%86%D1%83%D1%83%D0%BB%D0%B6-%D0%B1%D0%B0%D0%B9%D0%BD%D0%B0/&quot;&gt;BloombergTV Mongolia&lt;/a&gt; concluded that 62% of those surveyed take out loans for the holiday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve thought about the cost of Tsagaan Sar for a few years now, but not in absolute costs. I’ve written before about the &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/mongolian-data-stories/mongolians-are-more-in-debt-now-than-ever-7f797e448f77&quot;&gt;growing debt&lt;/a&gt; in Mongolia, and I wanted to see how the holiday impacted those who hold the greatest burden, the elders responsible for hosting 10’s or 100’s of guests. Phrased in a testable way:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Do pension or salary loans issuances show an increase for Tsagaan Sar separate from the rest of the year?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;loan-data&quot;&gt;Loan Data&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luckily, MongolBank, the country’s central bank, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mongolbank.mn/eng/dbliststatistic.aspx?id=02&quot;&gt;keeps statistics&lt;/a&gt; many statistics on loans. I chose salary and pension loans because they are issued to individuals and are not (directly) used to purchase real estate. Pension loans are of particular interest because they are given using the government pension of the person as collateral.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To do the analysis I downloaded the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mongolbank.mn/eng/dbliststatistic.aspx?id=02&quot;&gt;quarterly report&lt;/a&gt; of “ Individual and SME loans issued by banks” and separated out salary and pension loans issued. The data is only available quarterly or annually. Quarterly actually suits our needs quite well as Tsagaan Sar always takes place in Q1 while the exact dates move every year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/tsagaan-sar-debt-cycle/dataframe.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The head of our issued loans data. All numbers are in millions of MNT.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s first take a look at the time series of both salary and pension loans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/tsagaan-sar-debt-cycle/salary-loans-issued.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/tsagaan-sar-debt-cycle/pension-loans-issued.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other than the obvious large increases in both, the thing to notice is when each increases during the year. It is already noticeable that pension loans have a spike at the beginning of each year while salary loans spike later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To do a trend analysis we can use the handy &lt;a href=&quot;https://facebook.github.io/prophet/&quot;&gt;Prophet&lt;/a&gt; package from Facebook. There is a built-in seasonality tool that is perfect for this analysis. The tool is built on daily data analysis, so changes were made to accommodate a quarterly period (mainly reducing the &lt;a href=&quot;https://facebook.github.io/prophet/docs/seasonality,_holiday_effects,_and_regressors.html#fourier-order-for-seasonalities&quot;&gt;Fourier order&lt;/a&gt; for seasonality). The graphs below show the derived trends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/tsagaan-sar-debt-cycle/salary-loans-seasonal.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is important to remember when interpreting these graphs that as we only have one data point per quarter, Prophet is interpolating the trends between the quarters. For reference, quarters end March 31, June 30, September 30, and December 31.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Salary loans do show a large trend in Q1, but the largest trend appears to be in Q3. Perhaps parents trying to get enough money to pay for school tuition, clothes, etc.?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/tsagaan-sar-debt-cycle/pension-loan-seasonal.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pension loans have an obvious upward trend in Q1, with Q2 and Q3 being significantly smaller. Can we answer our question?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Do pension or salary loans issuances show an increase for Tsagaan Sar separate from the rest of the year?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, we certainly see a large increase in pension loans in Q1, which is when you would expect Tsagaan Sar expenditures, and therefore the need for cash. This certainly seems to fit with the narrative that the elderly are the most impacted, and are taking out loans specifically for the holiday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps if you visit a family next year for Tsagaan Sar you may consider giving a bit more money to help offset these costs.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Robert Ritz</name></author><category term="Tsagaan Sar" /><category term="debt" /><summary type="html">The entire country mobilizes weeks ahead of time to prepare. The city government, worried about traffic, only allows cars to drive during alternate days on the weekend. The bakeries are so consumed with making ul boov, a traditional pastry, that bread starts to disappear from store shelves the week before the holiday.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://mongoliandatastories.com/images/tsagaan-sar-debt-cycle/cover.jpeg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://mongoliandatastories.com/images/tsagaan-sar-debt-cycle/cover.jpeg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Open Data — Mongolia</title><link href="https://mongoliandatastories.com/open-data-mongolia" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Open Data — Mongolia" /><published>2018-10-22T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2018-10-22T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>https://mongoliandatastories.com/open-data-mongolia</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mongoliandatastories.com/open-data-mongolia">&lt;h4 id=&quot;where-to-find-data-onmongolia&quot;&gt;Where to find data on Mongolia&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Data is everything in today’s economy. Without it, businesses, governments, and even consumers can make effective decisions. Daily in my work as a university instructor and data scientist, I look for data that can explain, illustrate, and answer questions and issues about Mongolia and the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Data is the new oil. — Bryan Krzanich, Intel CEO&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Mongolia data (and the information that comes from it) are sometimes in short supply. So I wanted to put together a list of open data sources about Mongolia that can be used for analysis, research, business, etc. I will keep it updated as I find new sources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are data sources that contain many different categories of data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mongolian National Statistical Office&lt;/strong&gt;: A large amount of data on key macroeconomic and social data. This should be your first stop for national or regional data. Link: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.1212.mn/&quot;&gt;1212.mn&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;OpenAQ&lt;/strong&gt;: Air quality in Mongolia’s capital isn’t great, and OpenAQ aggregates air quality measurements for over 40 locations in Mongolia. Data goes back to 2015 for most sensors in UB and back to 2017 for those outside UB. Link: &lt;a href=&quot;https://openaq.org/#/countries/MN&quot;&gt;openaq.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;CrimeMap&lt;/strong&gt;: Mongolia’s national police agency runs a database of reported crimes that are able to be mapped. The service doesn’t work very often, but when it does it is pretty interesting to look at. Also, I made a dashboard last year that uses data scraped from the crime map that you can find &lt;a href=&quot;https://datastudio.google.com/open/1AUQACNWS9OMgiEvmJKFQPokI3Xw9NRbn&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Link: &lt;a href=&quot;http://crimemap.police.gov.mn/&quot;&gt;crimemap.police.gov.mn&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;M-Lab&lt;/strong&gt;: Measurement Lab (M-Lab) has a mission to monitor and report on network (internet) performance around the world. Their open dataset (accessible through Google BigQuery) includes Mongolia and is freely accessible. Ever wanted to know how Mongolian internet compares to other countries? Which ISP is better? M-Lab can answer that. Warning, this dataset requires some network and big data knowledge (or at least SQL database knowledge). Link: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.measurementlab.net/data/&quot;&gt;measurementlab.net&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mongolian Stock Exchange&lt;/strong&gt;: The Mongolian Stock Exchange (MSE) recently added semi-annual financial reports for over 100 list companies in English. However what is lacking are the official definitions of these terms according to Mongolian accounting standards (which are different from GAAP or IFRS). Link: &lt;a href=&quot;http://mse.mn/en/company_finance_report/120&quot;&gt;mse.mn&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mongolia GIS Data&lt;/strong&gt;: One extremely useful set of data is from Christopher Free, a quantitative ecologist at Rutgers University. He has collected GIS (geographic information systems) data for borders, roads, and zones for Ulaanbaatar and the aimags. This is useful if you want to model data over a geographic space, like market penetration, crime, etc. I hope to add to this dataset soon with a Khoroo and District shapefiles for Ulaanbaatar. Link: &lt;a href=&quot;https://marine.rutgers.edu/~cfree/gis-data/mongolia-gis-data/&quot;&gt;marine.rutgers.edu&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Government Ministries&lt;/strong&gt;: Each government ministry often has a statistics or data section on their website (often available only in Mongolian). Often the data is in the format of a PDF in a blog post, and isn’t very easy to access. The general government website zasag.mn has a list of government ministries and agencies along with their websites. Link: &lt;a href=&quot;http://zasag.mn/en/&quot;&gt;zasag.mn&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-need-for-a-datamarket&quot;&gt;The Need for a Data Market&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Above are the datasets that I am aware of. I’m sure there are more, and this highlights the need for a central data market for open data (or paid data). As Mongolia develops the need for high quality data, the demand for open data will skyrocket. I’ve considered doing this myself for some time, but the amount of work seems prohibitive for me alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy data hunting!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Robert Ritz</name></author><category term="open data" /><summary type="html">Where to find data on Mongolia</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://mongoliandatastories.com/images/open-data-mongolia/cover.jpeg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://mongoliandatastories.com/images/open-data-mongolia/cover.jpeg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Mongolia’s Economic Future is Chained to China</title><link href="https://mongoliandatastories.com/Mongolias-Economic-Future-Chained-China" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Mongolia’s Economic Future is Chained to China" /><published>2018-05-21T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2018-05-21T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>https://mongoliandatastories.com/Mongolias-Economic-Future-Chained-China</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mongoliandatastories.com/Mongolias-Economic-Future-Chained-China">&lt;h4 id=&quot;that-is-unless-mongolias-export-partners-diversify&quot;&gt;That is, unless Mongolia’s export partners diversify&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a rather gloomy title, but it is appropriate. There has been much discussion about diversifying the Mongolian economy to avoid the boom and bust cycle that has become common (see &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@turtogtokherdenebaatar/opportunity-to-diversify-the-mongolian-economy-3b7f178339b1&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://globalriskinsights.com/2016/04/mongolia-needs-to-diversify-to-avoid-recession/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.xinhuanet.com/english/2018-03/29/c_137074975.htm&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to name a few). Less has been discussed regarding diversifying trading partners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those familiar with the Mongolian economy, it is clear that China plays a big role in imports to the country. Yet I believe it is less known by the average Mongolian how closely exports are tied to China as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With all of the efforts of diversification, is the economy safer if nearly all of Mongolia’s exports go to one trading partner? Now factor in Chinese government whims to close the border &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.aljazeera.com/news/2016/12/china-blocks-mongolia-border-dalai-lama-visit-161210060313417.html&quot;&gt;whenever it fancys&lt;/a&gt;. This seems to be a recipe for economic uncertainty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To understand just how closely Mongolia’s exports are tied to China I gathered data from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.1212.mn/&quot;&gt;National Statistical Office&lt;/a&gt; and dug in. These data show Mongolia’s export value from 2005–2017 and is broken down by country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mapping-exports&quot;&gt;Mapping Exports&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First I wanted to visually see where Mongolia’s products and services are going around the world. I animated a global map, showing a new image for each year, and shaded the countries by the amount of exports going to that country. The darker the higher the value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/mongolia-chained-china/exports-over-time.gif&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;China remains dark throughout the period while other trading partners get significantly lighter. There is only one country that ends darker than it started, the United Kingdom. Interestingly enough back in 2005 the United States was number two, yet was still far away from the export value of China.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/mongolia-chained-china/exports-2005.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;charting-exports&quot;&gt;Charting Exports&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s take a look at real numbers now. But I warn you, they aren’t any prettier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/mongolia-chained-china/charting-exports.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here you can see the massive proportion of exports going to China from Mongolia. Every other country is dwarfed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;total-exports&quot;&gt;Total Exports&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course it’s not all doom and gloom. Since 2005 Mongolia’s exports have increased tremendously, propelling the country’s economy to new heights. The total value has gone from just over 1 billion USD to over 6 billion USD today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/mongolia-chained-china/exports-forecast.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Total value of Mongolian exports with a linear forecast. Error bars shown are based on a 95% confidence interval.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mongolian exports will continue to grow, and hopefully in a diversified way that includes more than natural resources and more than just China. Putting all your eggs in one basket is never a good idea.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Robert Ritz</name></author><category term="trade" /><category term="china" /><summary type="html">That is, unless Mongolia’s export partners diversify</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://mongoliandatastories.com/images/mongolia-chained-china/charting-exports.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://mongoliandatastories.com/images/mongolia-chained-china/charting-exports.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Mongolians are more in debt now than ever</title><link href="https://mongoliandatastories.com/Mongolian-more-in-debt-than-ever-before" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Mongolians are more in debt now than ever" /><published>2018-05-08T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2018-05-08T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>https://mongoliandatastories.com/Mongolian-more-in-debt-than-ever-before</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mongoliandatastories.com/Mongolian-more-in-debt-than-ever-before">&lt;h4 id=&quot;but-they-are-also-richer&quot;&gt;But they are also richer.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The economy is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2018-05-02/mongolia-s-swing-from-bust-to-boom-raises-question-can-it-last&quot;&gt;picking up steam&lt;/a&gt; in Mongolia. This is good news for the country’s businesses, who can hope the economic growth will translate to more money in peoples pockets. However, in a country that has experienced dramatic up and down swings of the economy, hope may not be in large supply.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I always tell my students, if you have a question, dig into it and test your hypothesis. My hypothesis is that debt levels may be reaching a critical amount that the economy can no longer bear. This will result in a lack of free cash for regular citizens and a weakening of non-mining economic growth. But hey, don’t take my word for it. Let’s look at the data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A huge amount of construction has taken place in recent years along with an increase in average salaries. Financing all of this building are commercial loans and also a government backed mortgage program offering the lowest rates in the country. This has led to an explosion of outstanding loans to finance the building of apartments and businesses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below I’ve charted outstanding loans and deposits from 2001–2016 (the most recent year available from the national statistical office). After the mining boom in the early 2010’s loans skyrocketed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/mongolians-more-debt/debt-chart.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The amount of outstanding loans is nearly 12.5 trillion MNT (just over 5 billion USD). At the same time deposits have grown significantly, but not at the same pace as loans. Ulaanbaatar leads the country in outstanding loans with 78% of all outstanding loans. These numbers combined with estimates in 2017 that there are &lt;a href=&quot;http://theubpost.mn/2017/02/19/free-up-prices-and-dismantle-monopolies/&quot;&gt;35–40 thousand empty apartments&lt;/a&gt; in Ulaanbaatar are quite concerning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is this debt trend national? Below I mapped the total of outstanding loans per capita in 2016 for each province (aimag) using Tableau. I excluded Ulaanbaatar as it highly imbalanced the map. As this is per capita we are balancing each provinces population to better compare them. For comparison Ulaanbaatar had a total outstanding loans per capita of 26.88 million MNT (nearly 11,000 USD).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/mongolians-more-debt/debt-map.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems pretty clear debt is consolidated primarily in Ulaanbaatar. This is both good and bad. Nearly half the population and most of the economic activity of the country is in Ulaanbaatar. However this also probably means the average UB’ier has more debt than the average person in the countryside. With &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/mongolian-data-stories/unemployment-in-mongolia-infographic-4595aab9bb85&quot;&gt;youth unemployment over 20%&lt;/a&gt;, debt in the nations capital may prove too much to bear.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Robert Ritz</name></author><category term="debt" /><category term="loans" /><summary type="html">But they are also richer.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://mongoliandatastories.com/images/mongolians-more-debt/debt-cover.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://mongoliandatastories.com/images/mongolians-more-debt/debt-cover.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">A first look at Mongolian crime data</title><link href="https://mongoliandatastories.com/A-First-Look-at-Mongolian-Crime-Data" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A first look at Mongolian crime data" /><published>2017-11-30T00:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2017-11-30T00:00:00+08:00</updated><id>https://mongoliandatastories.com/A-First-Look-at-Mongolian-Crime-Data</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mongoliandatastories.com/A-First-Look-at-Mongolian-Crime-Data">&lt;h4 id=&quot;note-from-april-2021-the-crimemap-referenced-in-this-no-longer-works-it-seems-the-government-of-mongolia-is-no-longer-supporting-this-project&quot;&gt;Note from April 2021: The crimemap referenced in this no longer works. It seems the government of Mongolia is no longer supporting this project.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few months ago I stumbled across a &lt;a href=&quot;http://crimemap.police.gov.mn/&quot;&gt;very interesting site&lt;/a&gt; made by the Mongolian national police that allows you to map crimes all around Mongolia. At the same time I was introduced to &lt;a href=&quot;https://datastudio.google.com&quot;&gt;Google Data Studio&lt;/a&gt;, a relatively new product from Google that allows you to create dashboards from live data. I thought it was a natural fit to mash the two together and make an attempt at a “Mongolian Crime Dashboard”. The rest of the article I will explain about this dataset, its features, and how I mashed it up with Data Studio.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are interested in viewing the dashboard click &lt;a href=&quot;https://datastudio.google.com/open/1AUQACNWS9OMgiEvmJKFQPokI3Xw9NRbn&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; or you can read on to see my dive into the data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/mongolian-crime-data/crimemap.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;What the Mongolian Crime Map looks like. Looks amazing but the locations are suspect. Source: &lt;a href=&quot;http://crimemap.police.gov.mn&quot;&gt;http://crimemap.police.gov.mn&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-the-mongolian-crime-map-is-different&quot;&gt;How the Mongolian Crime Map Is Different&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At first glance the Mongolian crime map was similar to &lt;a href=&quot;http://crime.chicagotribune.com/chicago/homicides&quot;&gt;crime maps of Chicago&lt;/a&gt;. You can visualize categories of crime over a specified time and it shows the locations of each crime. But the Mongolian data are less complete and messier than what would be ideal. The fields include the crime type, report number, date of report, location data down to the khoroo (neighborhood), and police station. However a few differences are clear when I dug in deeper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all the location data used to map the crimes on the map do not appear to be entirely reliable. Crimes appear to be mapped outside of their areas in some cases. Some crimes appear in entirely different countries. For example I found two crimes in Europe, a few in Siberia, and a few in China. So I determined using the mapped coordinates was a less than perfect way to use this data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second is the report location. It is a text field with the city/province, soum (like a county), district, and khoroo (sub-district / neighborhood). All of these details are separated by commas or spaces, with quite a bit of variability. I was able to use some regex functions in good old Excel to clean it up. Not ideal but workable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last is the time period available. Only 2015 and 2016 appeared to be complete. 2014 and 2017 seem to be incomplete as the total number of crimes is quite a bit lower. As such I focused on 2015–2016 for the dashboard. My theory as to the incomplete data for 2017 is either that they haven’t entered the reports or they only enter cases that are closed after a certain period of time. Either way it should be understood that there may be some missing data in the years 2015–2016 as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mongolias-national-statistical-office&quot;&gt;Mongolia’s National Statistical Office&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mongolia’s National Statistical Office (NSO) does a great job of collecting &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.1212.mn/Stat.aspx?LIST_ID=976_L23&amp;amp;type=tables&quot;&gt;crime totals&lt;/a&gt; as well. However their data are only reported down to the soum/county (outside Ulaanbaatar) or district level (inside Ulaanbaatar). This makes comparing neighborhoods difficult as some districts are quite large. Nearly 50 kilometers long in some cases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/mongolian-crime-data/ub-district.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Map of Ulaanbaatar districts. This is the smallest unit the NSO records crime data for. Credit: The Mongolist&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A major advantage is the NSO has complete data from 2010–2015, much longer than what is available from the Mongolian Crime Map. This historical data could be very valuable in things like &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sciencemag.org/news/2016/09/can-predictive-policing-prevent-crime-it-happens&quot;&gt;crime forecasting&lt;/a&gt;, which could be very helpful in policing. However this historical data is compiled yearly so we would be unable to see trends outside of year to year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-dashboard&quot;&gt;The Dashboard&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Google has come a long way since launching Data Studio last year, and the product is still in beta (per usual with Google). It is already a very powerful tool and clear competitor to &lt;a href=&quot;https://powerbi.microsoft.com/en-us/&quot;&gt;Microsoft’s Power BI&lt;/a&gt;. Even things like geo maps are relatively simple to make and are well documented. These are normally challenging to make as most software is geared to the developed world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/mongolian-crime-data/crime-dashboard1.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Mongolian crime dashboard. Google Data Studio is limited to mapping down to the province level.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Time series look great and are easily filterable, although are a bit messy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/mongolian-crime-data/crime-dashboard2.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Comparing Ulaanbaatar crime to provincial crime for Q4 2016.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is important to note that much of the labels are in Mongolian, but Google Translate does a pretty good job on most of the labels if needed. If you would like to view it in Data Studio &lt;a href=&quot;https://datastudio.google.com/open/1AUQACNWS9OMgiEvmJKFQPokI3Xw9NRbn&quot;&gt;click here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have suggestions or comments? Feel free to drop a comment below.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Robert Ritz</name></author><category term="crime" /><category term="government" /><category term="map" /><summary type="html">Note from April 2021: The crimemap referenced in this no longer works. It seems the government of Mongolia is no longer supporting this project.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://mongoliandatastories.com/images/mongolian-crime-data/crimemap.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://mongoliandatastories.com/images/mongolian-crime-data/crimemap.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>